纵览东欧与中亚，千城一面，皆出同源
Across Eastern Europe and Central Asia, entire cities were built using one system.
上至庙堂楼宇，下至砖瓦屋檐
From government towers to apartment blocks,
从学府到地铁，苏维埃的建筑美学，万变不离其宗
schools to metro stations, Soviet architecture followed a formula.
主打一个建造神速，维护低廉，且为国家机器量身打造
Fast to build, cheap to maintain, and designed to serve the state.
久而久之，这种实用主义竟自成一派：冰冷，且不断复制
Over time, that practically took on its own identity. Cold and repetitive.
时而雄伟壮观，时而阴郁沉闷，但你永远不会认错它
Sometimes impressive, sometimes bleak. But always unmistakable.
本期视频，咱们就来探究一下苏联当年为何如此大兴土木
In this video, we'll look at why the Soviet Union built the way they did.
它的目标究竟为何
What it was trying to achieve,
以及为何在帝国崩塌数十年后，这些遗产仍旧屹立不倒
and why so much of it is standing decades after the collapse.
苏维埃联盟，诞生于1917年的俄国革命之后
The Soviet Union was formed after the Russian Revolution in 1917.
在此之前，俄罗斯帝国由君主统治
Before that, the Russian Empire was ruled by a monarchy,
财富与土地集中在少数人手中
where wealth and land were concentrated in the hands of a few.
大多数人穷困潦倒，并对这种生活习以为常
Most people were poor and used to that way of life.
一战期间，崩溃与饥荒肆虐
During World War I, where collapse and famine were rampant,
一个名为“布尔什维克”的团体在现代俄罗斯掌握了政权
a group called the Bolsheviks took power in modern day Russia.
并试图在一个截然不同的体系上重建这个国家
And tried to build the country based on an entirely different system.
这个体系拒绝资本主义、宗教和私有财产
This system rejected capitalism, religion, and private property.
也就是那个“大名鼎鼎”的共产主义的分支
A branch of the infamous communism.
在苏联的设想中，工人阶级将掌控经济并手握大权
In the USSR, the idea was that workers would have control over the economy and have more power.
而一切事务皆由国家中央统筹规划
While everything would be centrally planned by the state.
不过，这也不完全是共产主义
That is not exactly what communism is though.
它只是一个基于其理念的系统
It's just a system based off of it.
这是一场巨大的政治变革
This was a huge political shift.
它改变了一切
It changed everything.
城市的布局方式
How cities were laid out.
人们的生活方式
How people lived.
以及建筑的设计理念
And how buildings were designed.
在他们看来，建筑必须反映新的制度
In their view, architecture had to reflect the new system.
它必须服务于集体
It needed to serve the collective.
而非个人的品味或奢华
Not the individual tastes or luxury.
苏维埃建筑的基调，便由此开始
This is where the tone of the Soviet architecture begins.
实用至上，意识形态挂帅，并旨在将其秩序强加于人民
Practical, ideological, and built to impose order upon its people.
早期，国家支持实验性的建筑风格
Early on, the state supported experimental architecture.
1920年代，一股激进设计的浪潮汹涌而至
In the 1920s, there was a wave of radical design.
尤其是建构主义
Especially constructivism.
其核心在于实用性、几何形态，以及工业时代的专属材料
Which focused on utility, geometry, and materials of the industrial age.
例如混凝土、钢铁和玻璃
Such as concrete, steel, and glass.
这些建筑看起来与俄罗斯以往的任何风格都截然不同
These buildings looked different from anything Russia had seen before.
它们不再模仿古老的教堂或宫殿
They didn't imitate old churches or palaces.
它们专为满足工人阶级的需求而生
They were designed to suit the needs of the workers.
配备共享厨房和公共空间，极尽“功能至上”之所能，而非“装饰”
With shared kitchens, communal spaces, and an emphasis on function over decoration.
政府宣称他们几乎消灭了无家可归的现象
The government claimed to have pretty much eliminated homelessness.
这话大概不假，但它回避了因住房短缺而导致的局促居住条件
And while probably true, it fails to recognize the many housing shortages that led to cramped conditions.
莫斯科的纳科姆芬大楼便是一例
One example of this is the Narkomfin building in Moscow.
它堪称新苏维埃公民应如何生活的样板间
It was a kind of prototype for how the new Soviet citizen was supposed to live.
减少隐私，增加社群，大把时间投入集体生活
Less privacy, more community, and more time spent in collective life.
但到了1930年代，这种自由消失了
But by the 1930s, that freedom disappeared.
到了斯大林时代，国家机器要求掌控生活的方方面面
Under Stalin, the state demanded control over every part of life.
包括建筑的外观
Including how buildings looked.
现代主义设计被弃置一旁，取而代之的是更传统，也更“重量级”的风格
Modernist designs were pushed aside in favor of something more traditional, but bigger and heavier.
斯大林的建筑带回了过去的元素
Stalin's architecture brought back elements from the past.
廊柱，拱门，以及绝对对称
Columns, arches, and symmetry.
但剥去了其中的温度
But stripped them of warmth.
这些建筑旨在彰显国家的强盛力量
These buildings were meant to show the strength of the state.
莫斯科的“七姐妹”便是其中的著名典范
A famous example of this are the Seven Sisters in Moscow.
这些巨型摩天楼，其设计初衷便是要与纽约的天际线一较高下
Enormous skyscrapers designed to rival the skyline of New York.
但它们被赋予了截然不同的精神内核
But they were built in a completely different spirit.
它们无关创新，也无关个人表达
They weren't about innovation or individual expression.
在地面上，苏维埃建筑的压迫感开始显现
At ground level, this is where the feeling of Soviet architecture starts to settle in.
即便那些算不上高耸入云的建筑，也透着一股沉重感
Even the buildings that aren't especially tall feel heavy.
这些建筑时常让人感觉与“人”的尺度格格不入
The buildings often feel disconnected from human scale.
它们硕大无朋，却没有任何细节可供玩味
They're enormous and have no detail to hold onto.
毫无变化，毫无个性
No variation or expression.
只有重复
Just repetition.
一条走廊可能无限延伸，色彩与质地却一成不变
A hallway might stretch on with no change in color or texture.
整个街区可能看起来就像是复制粘贴的
An entire district might look copy pasted.
这与计划经济的逻辑如出一辙
And that is the same logic that planned the economy.
1953年斯大林去世后，住房问题成了重中之重
After Stalin died in 1953, housing became the main priority.
城市过度拥挤，苏联人口增长迅猛
The cities were overcrowded and the Soviet population was growing very quickly.
继任者尼基塔·赫鲁晓夫
The next leader, Nikita Khrushchev,
发起了一场大规模建设运动，核心是速度与效率
introduced a massive construction campaign focused on speed and efficiency.
这导致了“赫鲁晓夫楼”的遍地开花
This led to the spread of Khrushchevkas.
那些用预制板材拼凑起来的五层混凝土公寓楼
Five-story concrete apartment blocks built from prefabricated panels.
它们造价低廉，规格统一，易于搭建
They were cheap, standardized, and easy to build.
隔热性能极差，墙体薄如蝉翼，布局嘛……聊胜于无
They had poor insulation, thin walls, and basic layouts.
但对许多家庭而言，这已是他们有生以来拥有的第一套私人公寓了
But for many families, they were the first private apartments they ever had.
其结果
The result
便是整个苏联境内建筑风格的“天下大同”
was a kind of architectural uniformity across the entire USSR.
从爱沙尼亚到塔吉克斯坦，住房看起来几乎一模一样
From Estonia to Tajikistan, the housing looked almost the same.
这当然是有意为之
That was by design.
莫斯科需要控制权，尤其是在斯大林治下
Moscow wanted control, especially under Stalin.
而标准化让这成为可能
And standardization made that possible.
所有的材料都一样
The materials were all the same.
布局一样，城市规划也一样
The layouts were the same, as well as the urban planning.
要理解这一点，必须将其置于苏联的宏观结构中
It's important to understand how this fit into the larger structure of the Soviet Union.
它不是一个国家
It wasn't one country.
它是一个由15个不同共和国组成的联盟
It was a union of 15 different republics.
每个共和国在总规划中都有自己的角色
And each had a role in its overall plan.
比如，乌克兰是联盟的“大粮仓”
Ukraine, for example, was the agricultural base.
哈萨克斯坦为太空计划提供支持
Kazakhstan supported the space program.
乌兹别克斯坦负责种棉花
Uzbekistan grew cotton.
而俄罗斯则主导军事和重工业
And Russia led the military and heavy industry.
建筑风格也遵循着这些角色定位
The architecture followed those roles.
无数的城市拔地而起，只为支撑矿山、电厂或研究中心
Entire cities were built from scratch to support mines, power plants, or research centers.
而在此期间，苏联确实在飞速猛进
And during this time, the USSR was making serious advances.
它成了第一个发射卫星、将人类送入太空，并建成永久空间站的国家
It became the first country to launch a satellite, send a person into space, and build permanent space stations.
尽管美国最终成功登月，但早期的太空竞赛，实则由苏维埃一手遮天
While the US eventually made it to the moon, the early space race was actually dominated by the Soviets.
与此同时，重大的隐患也在暗处滋生
At the same time, major problems were spreading underneath.
1930年代
In the 1930s,
强制集体化引发了大饥荒，导致农村数百万人丧生
forced collectivization led to famines that killed millions in rural areas,
在乌克兰和哈萨克斯坦尤为惨烈
especially in Ukraine and Kazakhstan.
庞大的基础设施项目是依靠强迫劳动建成的
Huge infrastructure projects were built using forced labor.
即使在后来更稳定的领导下，物资短缺也已是家常便饭
Even later, under more stable leadership, shortages were common.
人们有住的地方，但时常没有足够的食物、药品或可靠的暖气
People had places to live, but sometimes not enough food, medicine, or reliable heating.
报道这些数据的可靠信源少之又少
Reputable sources reporting these stats were scarce.
关于苏联日常生活的真实信息，一直被双方操纵
The real information about daily life in the USSR has been manipulated by both sides,
无论是西方还是苏联自己，都对其进行了“艺术加工”
the West and the Soviets themselves, each with their own spin to it.
每当人们谈及冷战，“登月”似乎总是那个一锤定音的终局
When people talk about the Cold War, the moon landing usually comes up as the final word.
仿佛那个瞬间就结束了竞赛，美国大获全胜
As if that one moment ended the race, leaving the USA victorious.
然而事实并非如此
But it didn't.
况且在其他多数指标上，苏联都遥遥领先
And by most other measures, the Soviets were ahead.
1957年，苏联发射了人类第一颗人造卫星“斯普特尼克” (Sputnik)
In 1957, the Soviet Union launched Sputnik, the first artificial satellite.
一个沙滩球大小的抛光金属球，它的哔哔声响彻每片大陆
A polished metal sphere, about the size of a beach ball, that beeped over every continent
证明了苏联有能力将物体送入轨道
and proved the USSR could launch objects into orbit.
接着是莱卡 (Laika)，第一只进入太空的动物
Next came Laika, the first animal in space.
接着是尤里·加加林，飞天第一人
Then Yuri Gagarin, the first human.
接着是瓦莲京娜·捷列什科娃，第一位女性
Then Valentina Tereshkova, the first woman.
再然后是首次太空行走，首次月球软着陆，首次有探测器抵达
Then the first spacewalk, the first soft landing on the moon, the first probes to reach.
金星和火星，以及第一座空间站
Venus and Mars, the first space station.
显而易见，苏联在太空竞赛上是“卷王”本王了
As you can see, the USSR were big on the space race.
十多年来，他们一直霸占着榜首
For over a decade, they dominated it.
1969年美国登月，对山姆大叔而言无疑是重大胜利
The US landing on the moon in 1969 was a major victory for the USA.
但这几乎也说得上是他们“唯几”的胜利
But it was also one of the only ones.
在那之后，美国人似乎就偃旗息鼓了
After that, the Americans sort of stopped going.
但苏联人可没歇着
But the Soviets didn't.
他们不断发射，建造，测试，并精进他们的系统
They kept launching, building, testing, and refining their systems.
时至今日，基于苏联设计的“联盟号”火箭
Even today, Soyuz rockets based on Soviet designs
仍在兢兢业业地运送宇航员进入轨道
are still used to send astronauts into orbit.
但双方的宣传机器都极大地扭曲了事实
But the propaganda on both sides really distorted the truth.
美国佬夸大战功，苏联人则忙着掩盖败绩
The US exaggerated its victories, and the USSR hit its failures.
有宇航员牺牲，有发射失败
There were cosmonauts who died and failed launches.
有许多任务从未被报道
There were missions that never got reported.
但西方世界同样如此
But the same was true in the West.
只是包装得更光鲜亮丽
Only more polished.
双方都将太空作为彰显权力、智慧与合法性的图腾
Both sides used space as a symbol of power, intelligence, and legitimacy.
这在他们各自的情报机构中可见一斑
That is shown in their respective intelligence agencies.
至于KGB和CIA的恩怨情仇，且听下回分解
But the KGB and the CIA will be discussed in a future video.
从1960年代末到1980年代
Soviet buildings from the late 1960s through the 1980s
苏联建筑时常呈现出一种怪诞的、未来主义的形态
often took on strange, futuristic forms.
圆形屋顶，混凝土飞翼，建筑被塑造成飞碟、穹顶或金字塔的模样
Circular roofs, concrete wings, buildings shaped like discs, domes, or pyramids.
谈不上什么装饰，材料也还是老几样
Not decorative, but still made from the same materials.
依旧是批量生产，但开始整点不一样的活儿了
Still mass produced, but now reaching for something different.
这是一种炫技，表明苏联不再满足于“活着”
It was a way of showing that the USSR wasn't just surviving anymore.
它在竞争，它在进步
It was competing, and it was advancing.
这一点在科研建筑、天文台、剧院和纪念碑上体现得淋漓尽致
This was clearest in scientific buildings, observatories, theaters, and monuments.
像加里宁格勒的“苏维埃宫”
Structures like the House of Soviets in Kaliningrad,
或乌克兰科技研究所
or the Ukrainian Institute of Scientific and Technological Research,
它们不遵循传统布局
don't follow traditional layouts.
感觉更像是机器，而非建筑
They feel more like machines than buildings.
带着一种粗野的，仿佛天外来客般的现代主义
Kind of brutal, alien modernism.
保加利亚的冰峰纪念碑，最著名的苏维埃时代废弃建筑之一
The Ibuz Lutsa Monument in Bulgaria, one of the most famous abandoned Soviet-era structures,
被设计成一个混凝土UFO，安放在山巅之上
was designed like a concrete UFO, placed on top of a mountain.
它本是为共产主义运动献上的赞歌，如今却只剩一片空寂
It was supposed to honor the communist movement, but now it sits empty.
到了1980年代，苏联经济已是日薄西山
By the 1980s, the Soviet economy was in decline.
军费开支难以为继
Military spending was unsustainable,
粮食短缺卷土重来
food shortages returned,
其核心价值观也在领导人的更迭中消散殆尽
and its core values had disappeared while sifting through different leaders.
那个曾让苏联飞速崛起的中央集权体制，如今却成了它的绊脚石
The same centralized system that had allowed the USSR to grow so fast, was now keeping stuck.
创新停滞，责任缺失，消费文化几近于无
There was no innovation, no accountability, and almost no consumer culture.
人们拥有住房、教育和基本医疗，但仅此而已
People had homes, education, and basic healthcare, but not much beyond that.
它没能跟上自己的发展脚步
It did not keep up with its growth,
因此，你随处可见那种疲态
and because of that, you can see the fatigue.
建筑变得更廉价，更千篇一律，也更疏于维护
Buildings became cheaper, more repetitive, and more neglected.
即使是那些未来主义的杰作也未能幸免
Even the futuristic ones couldn't escape it.
油漆剥落，电梯停摆，混凝土开裂，最要命的是，没钱了
Paint chipped, elevators broke, concrete crap, and there was no money.
到1991年，苏联在戈尔巴乔夫治下解体
By 1991, the Soviet Union dissolved under Gorbachev.
15个新国家诞生了
Fifteen new countries emerged.
国家规划了每座建筑，每条街道，每栋公寓
The state had planned every building, every street, every apartment block.
而今，它消失了
And now, it was gone.
剩下的，是衰败与幸存的奇妙混合体
What's left is a strange mix of decay and survival.
在莫斯科，“七姐妹”中的几座仍在使用
In Moscow, some of the Seven Sisters are still in use.
一座现在是豪华酒店
One is now a luxury hotel.
另一些则成了政府的办公楼
Others are government offices.
在中亚，苏联建筑半是废墟，矗立在现代玻璃幕墙旁
In Central Asia, Soviet buildings sit half abandoned next to glass towers.
在乌克兰和白俄罗斯的乡村，整个城镇仿佛冻结在原地
In rural Ukraine and Belarus, entire towns are frozen in place.
旧工厂，旧住宅区，依然矗立，但正缓慢地分崩离析
Old factories, old housing blocks still standing, but slowly falling apart.
这些建筑并未随风而逝
The architecture didn't disappear.
它们仍在那里，因为它们本就为持久而建
It's still there because it was built to last.
细节已陨，而风骨犹存
Not in detail, but in structure.
它们大多“堆料过猛”，浇筑了足量混凝土，足以抵抗时间与忽视
Most of it was overbuilt, poured with enough concrete to resist time and neglect.
这种风格如此普遍，如此雷同，以至于你穿行数千公里
The style was so widespread and so repetitive that you can travel thousands of kilometers
却依然感觉仿佛从未离开
and still feel like you haven't left.
如今它们之所以显得诡异，是因其本应代表一个“从未到来”的未来
What makes it eerie now is that these buildings were meant to represent a future that never arrived.
它们诞生之时，那个系统曾笃信自己会千秋万代
They were designed during a time when the system believed it would last forever.
如今它们栖身于一个不同的世界
Now they sit in a different world.
一个早已抛下它们、滚滚向前的世界
A world that moved on without them.
然而，它们仍在定义着它们所在的城市
And yet they still define the cities they were built for.
即使旗帜早已更换
Even after the flags changed.
即使政权早已倾覆
Even after the governments fell.
苏维埃的建筑，依然故我
Soviet architecture remained.
你无法忽视它的存在
And you can't ignore it.